Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records LSC.1434
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Historical Murals and Afro-American Art Collection Files, 1948-2000
  - Historical Murals files, 1947-1949
    - Mural artists conference notes and research, 1948-1949 (Box 264, Folder 6)
      Materials include Biddy Mason biography, references for subjects relating to murals, transcript of telephone conversation between Woodruff, Alston, Houston, Beavers and Hickman, Report on Meeting with Miriam Matthews, Titus Alexander and Executive Committee, Executive Committee comments on first mural sketches, Suggestions for Murals by Miriam Matthews, Verna Hickman's notes on Mural Conference, Mural Conference Minutes, Robert C. Owens biography, Philip Carter's mural research, Suggested Subjects Relating to Painted Murals, List of Los Angeles County Historical Landmarks, Digest of Minutes of the General Conference on Historical Landmarks and Founding of Los Angeles notes by Titus Alexander.
    - Mary Ellen "Mammy" Pleasant photostats, 1948 (Box 264, Folder 7)
      Materials include photostats of Mammy Pleasant's Memoirs and Autobiography and "The Queen of the Voodoos" San Francisco Chronicle article.
    - Mural photographs, circa 1949 (Box 264, Folder 8)
      Victoria Shorey Francis was a direct descendent of William Shorey, a whale boat captain during the late 1890s who operated in the waters just outside San Francisco.
      Photographs of the murals include an image of Victoria Shorey Francis from Oakland standing in front of the murals.
    - Murals correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 264, Folder 9)
      Correspondence includes letters from George A. Beavers, Jr., Verna A. Hickman, Titus Alexander, Leonard Grimes, Charles Alston, Hale Woodruff and the California Centennial Commission concerning the contribution of Negro pioneers. Materials also include a report of the Murals Research Tour and a Public Relations memo concerning research material for the murals.
    - Route of the Mural Research Tour in California, 1948 August 16-September 3 (Box 264, Folder 10)
      Materials include an itinerary and route with detailed description for points of interest.
    - Mural research tour report, 1948 (Box 264, Folder 11)
      Materials include the Mural research tour report, Norman O. Houston report on mural painting, sculptor and art, Memo of telephone conversation between Hickman, Alston and Woodruff, transcripts of telephone conversations between George A. Beavers, Jr. and Charles Alston and Beavers and Hale Woodruff, correspondence from Alston and Woodruff to Hickman and Beavers and transcript of a telephone conversation between Beavers, Hickman, Alston and Woodruff.
    - Murals press and releases, 1949-1958 (Box 264, Folder 12)
      Materials include press clippings, Murals on California History press releases and color reproductions of the Alston panel.
    - Mural unveiling photographs, 1949 August 19 (Box 264, Folder 13)
      Photographs include images of Norman O. Houston, Julia Metcalf, Nora Holt, Titus Alexander, Aimee Torriani, Sharon Patterson, Father H. Randolph Moore, Charlotta A. Bass, Mary Woods, Gladys Owens Smith, George A. Beavers, Jr., Edgar J. Johnson, Miriam Matthews, Mercer Z. Ray, Robert W. Smith, Arthur J. Williams, Helen Hodge (Batiste), Bertha B. Nickerson, Verna Hickman, John Payton, Seth Lee, R.W. Smith, Henry H. Towles, Thaddius McCray and Margaret Mosley.
    - Historical Murals booklets, undated (Box 264, Folder 14)
      Materials include four Historical Murals booklets, each with a different cover.
    - Conference with Mural Artists transcript, 1948 September 7 (Box 265, Folder 1)
      This conference was convened by the Executive Committee at the GSM Home Office. Members of the Executive Committee who were present include the following: George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston and Edgar J. Johnson. Also in attendance were Head of Public Relations Verna Hickman, her staff member, Leonard Grimes, artists Hale Woodruff and Charles Alston and researchers Miriam Matthews and Titus Alexander.
    - California Centennial press release, circa 1949 (Box 265, Folder 2)
      Press release draft, "The California Negro (1512-1949) California Centennial Ignores Negro History" concerning the presence of GSM's Historical Murals in contrast to the absence of early Negro Pioneers within the Centennial program.
    - Murals press release, 1949 July (Box 265, Folder 3)
      Five copies of the "Murals On California History" press release written by Public Relations Administrator Verna Hickman.
    - Ebony reprints, 1949 November (Box 265, Folder 4)
      Three reprints of the Ebony article, "California Centennial: Rich epochal history of Negro pioneers in building of West chronicled in murals at new Golden State insurance building."
    - Blacks in America supplements, 1970 March 23 (Box 265, Folder 5)
      Seven copies of The Sacramento Union's "Blacks in America" supplement featuring the GSM Historical Murals on its front and back cover.
    - Murals clipping, 1987 January 30 (Box 265, Folder 6)
      Two copies of the Los Angeles Herald Examiner clipping, "A Guide to Black Los Angeles: Take a field or two into the past."
    - Founding of Los Angeles articles, undated (Box 265, Folder 7)
      Articles include two copies of "Nuggets of History: Highlights from California's Past" by Jack D. Forbes of the Foundation for Inter-Ethnic Understanding and two copies of "Los Angeles: The City is Founded."
    - California historical research file, 1947-1955 (Box 266, Folder 1-2)
      Folder 1: Materials include the following booklets: Mission San Luis Rey, The Sutro Story, Effects of the Community Property Law on Residents of California and Facts about Joint Tenancies, Greetings from Carmel by the Sea, The Founders of Los Angeles by John M. Weatherwax and dedicated to Charlotta A. Bass, Do You Know? Facts about our State Library, Book Resources of San Francisco Bay Area compiled by the California Library Association, Eight Mural Paintings by Charles Hoffbauer, California: The Golden State compiled by Secretary of State Frank M. Jordan, California Missions postcards and Sue Bailey Thurman's Pioneers of Negro Origin in California. Thurman's spiral-bound book includes chapters on Biddy Mason, Mary E. Pleasant and the Golden State Murals as well as two notes of gratitude inscribed by the author to GSM's Verna Hickman for her assistance with this project.
      Folder 2: Materials include a photo of Titus Alexander and World Champion Olympians and a photo of Negro DWP employees working on the construction of the transmission line from Hoover Dam power plant to Los Angeles. Materials also include a Chicago Defender column by Langston Hughes which discusses GSM's historical murals, the California Historical Society's Centennial Calendar, correspondence from George A. Beavers, Jr. to the Chairman of the California Centennials Commission offering access to GSM's research materials that document the participation of Negro citizens in the events selected for the historical caravan, a Golden Anniversary Commemorative Edition of Organized Labor, the A.F. of L. Building Trades weekly newspaper and The Prudential Insurance Company's "Seventy-Five Years Ago in the West" 75th Anniversary booklet.
    - Murals and founders portraits photographs, 1949 August 19 (Box 266, Folder 3-4)
      Photographs include images of the murals, the murals unveiling ceremony and the unveiling of portraits of GSM co-founders George A. Beavers, Jr. and Norman O. Houston.
    - New slides of Historical Murals, 1979 January (Box 266, Folder 5)
      Color slides of the murals taken by Armando Solis.
    - Historical Murals booklets, undated (Box 266, Folder 6)
      Materials include twenty-one copies of the Historical Murals booklets.
    - Hale Woodruff panel photograph, circa 1960s (Box 266, Folder 7)
      One 11" x 14" black and white photo of the Hale Woodruff "Settlement and Development" panel includes a view of the lobby, front desk and GSM clerk.
    - Murals sketches, circa 1948 (Box 266, Folder 8)
      Materials include black and white copies of color panel sketches by Charles Alston and Hale Woodruff. Each sketch includes a legend on its back side.
    - Murals unveiling recordings, 1949 August 19 (Box 267)
      Recordings of the murals unveiling ceremony include the following: Four 1/4" open reel audio recordings and a transfer of this ceremony on two compact discs.
  - Afro-American Art Collection files, 1949, 1960s-1970s, 1985-1986, 1993, 1998-2000
    The GSM Afro-American Art Collection was conceived as a showplace for the works of Negro artists and dedicated in commemoration of GSM's 40th anniversary in 1965. According to curator William Pajaud, there were many reasons for establishing the collection but primarily the Company felt the need to create an atmosphere that would foster pride among people, reacquaint Black Americans with their artistic heritage, discover talent among the youth of its community and to establish the first such collection in the West. Student tours of the collection and related art scholarships strengthened ties between the Company and the communities it served.
    Materials include correspondence, inventories, brochures, scrapbooks and albums, public relations files, invoices, appraisal reports, exhibit labels, publications, photographs, proof sheets and audiovisual materials.
    - Richmond Barthe file, 1948-1949 (Box 268, Folder 1)
      Materials include correspondence between Verna Hickman and Richmond Barthe concerning the creation of the William Nickerson, Jr. bust, photographs of Barthe's sculpture, his resume and a clipping concerning his first one man show in New Jersey.
    - Architectural agreement, 1960-1961 (Box 268, Folder 2)
      Materials include correspondence between Norman O. Houston and Architect Claude H. Grimes and an agreement between GSM and Grimes.
    - Southwest Wave clipping, 1965 July 25 (Box 268, Folder 3)
      Southwest Wave article, "Negro Art Displayed" discusses GSM's newly installed art collection.
    - Negro art collection additions and inventory, 1967-1968 (Box 268, Folder 4)
      Additions include a piece by Michael K. Perry and two pieces by Arnold Love.
    - Art collection ad and bio sheet, circa 1968 (Box 268, Folder 5)
      Materials include a GSM Negro Art Collection advertisement and a biographical form for artists.
    - Art loan correspondence, 1968, 1978-1981, 1992-1993, 1998 (Box 268, Folder 6)
      Letters discuss the loan of art to GSM for special events and the loan of pieces from GSM's collection.
    - Art collection inventories, 1968-1969 (Box 268, Folder 7)
    - Afro-American Art Collection scrapbook, 1960s-1970s (Box 268, Folder 8)
      Materials include inventories and records of loans, acquisitions, returns, contracts with donors such as Miriam Matthews, correspondence with artists such as Charles White, proposal for a Beulah Woodard Sculpture collection, GSM's Museum progress report, images of the art work, photographs of GSM employees, executives at the art collection dedication, Golden Pen issues, art collection ads, clippings and Charles White booklet.
    - Art collection brochure, 1973 (Box 268, Folder 9)
      Materials include an illustrated cover for a GSM Afro-American art booklet.
    - Exhibit agreement, 1974-1975 (Box 268, Folder 10)
      Materials include temporary exhibit agreement and correspondence exhibitions.
    - LACMA, 1976-1990 (Box 268, Folder 11)
      Correspondence from the Los Angeles County Museum of Art concerning loan agreements for its "Two Centuries of Black American Art" exhibition.
    - Art collection scrapbook #1, 1976, 1978, 1985 (Box 268, Folder 12)
      Materials include Black Art: an international quarterly, Travel & Art, correspondence and workshop evaluations for Rhapsodies in Black: Art of the Harlem Renaissance.
    - Art collection file, 1977-1978 (Box 269, Folder 1)
      Materials include GSM Afro-American Art Collection: Why? paper, Ethnic and National Collections in the Los Angeles Area compiled by Los Angeles Public Library Resource Specialist Sally Dumaux and a Comparison of Two Corporate Art Collections student paper.
    - Art Collection Album #3, circa 1977-1978 (Box 269, Folder 2-5)
      Materials include biographical forms for artists and information sheets for each piece in the collection.
    - Art collection inventories, 1978, 1987 (Box 269, Folder 6)
      Inventories include the following information: Artist, title, medium, dimension, date of execution, condition, value, owner and location.
    - Black Art Museums, 1978, 1980-1985, 1998-1999 (Box 269, Folder 7)
      Materials include correspondence between GSM's William Pajaud and curators of African American museums, ARTnews The Insider's Guide to Buying and Enjoying Art booklet, Drawings of Van Slater booklet, Winston-Salem Delta Fine Arts, Inc. brochure, DuSable Museum of African American History, Inc. Annual Report and GSM's Selected Pieces from the Afro-American Art Collection booklet.
    - Charles White tribute, 1979 November (Box 269, Folder 8)
      Materials include A Memorial Jubilee... A Tribute to Charles White program, correspondence and the poem, "Victory of King Charlie" by Jacinto Anielle Rhines, Jr.
    - White on Black Art file, 1979 (Box 269, Folder 9)
      Materials include White on Black Art presentation transcript which includes Ivan J. Houston's introduction and closing and Charles White's slide presentation featuring the Golden State Mutual Afro-American Art Collection.
    - GSM Art Collection presentation transcripts, 1978 (Box 270, Folder 1)
      Transcripts include the following titles: Charles White on Black Art, Black Masters at GSM, Public Relations Afro-American Art Collection slide presentation and Golden State Art Collection: A Study in Black Tradition.
    - GSM art collection advertisement, 1978 (Box 270, Folder 2)
      File includes the February/March edition of Travel & Art: A Magazine of Black Cultural Interest. There is a "Where Can You Find the Largest Collection of Black Art West of Chicago?" advertisement for the GSM Afro-American Art Collection on page 22.
    - Art Collection album #4, 1970s-1990s (Box 270, Folder 3-5)
      Materials include artist biographies, cards which depict and describe the collection, gallery invoices, contracts, correspondence and art work slides.
    - Afro-American Museum of Detroit, 1980, 1983, 1988 (Box 271, Folder 1)
      Materials include correspondence between William Pajaud and the Afro-American Museum of Detroit and the California Afro-American Museum.
    - Museum of African American Art, 1981-1983, 1987 (Box 271, Folder 2)
      Materials include correspondence of gratitude from Museum of African American Art (M.A.A.A.) Director Mary Jane Hewitt to William Pajaud for his role as a founding member of the Museum's Board of Directors and Golden State Mutual's M.A.A.A. membership cards.
    - California Afro-American Museum press kit, 1982-1983, 1986 (Box 271, Folder 3)
      Press kit includes California Afro-American Museum (C.A.A.M.) brochures, an Afro-Am newsletter, Board of Directors contact sheet and an Olympic Arts Festival catalog for the C.A.A.M. exhibit, The Black Olympians.
    - The Studio Museum of Harlem, 1981-1985 (Box 271, Folder 4)
      Materials include correspondence from Directors, a catalog for the permanent collection, anniversary invitations and loan documentation for Charles White's "General Moses."
    - DuSable Museum/Chicago, 1983-1985 (Box 271, Folder 5)
      Materials include correspondence from Executive Director Margaret Burroughs concerning the Tanner Painting Restorations, a receipt for the restorations, a Heritage Calendar, newsletter and annual report.
    - Art collection public relations materials, undated (Box 271, Folder 6)
      Materials include two GSM Afro-American Art Collection booklets and a paste-up board for an art collection advertisement.
    - California Afro-American Museum, 1984, 1986-1987 (Box 271, Folder 7)
      Correspondence from C.A.A.M. curators to William Pajaud, loan forms and a C.A.A.M. informational booklet.
    - White on Black Art Campaign, 1984 (Box 271, Folder 8)
      Materials include correspondence to William Pajaud from Frances White and the Friends of Charles White concerning the 4th Annual Charles White Festival, a Charles White card with a note to Bill from Fran and A Brief History of the Charles White Art Festival.
    - Studio Museum 17th Anniversary, 1985 (Box 271, Folder 9)
      Materials include Studio Museum in Harlem 17th Anniversary correspondence, program and itinerary for Honoree Ivan J. Houston who was presented an original print by Jacob Lawrence entitled "The Builders" in recognition of GSM's art collection.
    - Art collection inventories, 1990-1993, 1999-2000 (Box 271, Folder 10)
      Materials include inventories and lists of art label contents for the GSM Art Collection.
    - Art Collection invoices, 1992-1993 (Box 271, Folder 11-12)
      Materials include names, artists and values of works on loan to the Golden State Minority Foundation.
    - Houston Museum of Fine Arts, 1994, 1996-1998 (Box 271, Folder 13)
      Materials include correspondence from Curator Alvia J. Wardlaw regarding "The Art of John Biggers: View from the Upper Room" exhibition and the loan of GSM's Biggers drawing entitled "Man" and photocopies of related press clippings.
    - Smithsonian, 1994, 1996-2000 (Box 271, Folder 14)
      Correspondence from Smithsonian staff regarding GSM art loans for traveling exhibitions.
    - The California Collectors' Series press kit, 1994 (Box 271, Folder 15)
      Press kit includes correspondence from Founder and President Royce H. Vaughn, his business card, press releases and postcards.
    - Art collection inventories, 1996, 2002-2003 (Box 271, Folder 16)
      Materials include inventories, lists of missing work and appraisals.
    - Art collection master list, 1996, 2000-2005 (Box 272, Folder 1)
      Materials include multiple inventories and public relations reports.
    - Artwork - Pajaud, 1998, 2002-2003 (Box 272, Folder 2)
      Materials include a profile on Pajaud from international quarterly, Black Art, C.A.A.M. loan form, reviews of Pajaud's work and correspondence from GSM Assistant Marketing Director Clifton D. Blevins, II.
    - Loans to collection, 1999 (Box 272, Folder 3)
      Materials include correspondence concerning a photography loan for the book, The Art Riddle Contest and Art Collection adhesive labels which include title, artist, medium and owner.
    - GSM Art Collection, 1998, 2000-2005 (Box 272, Folder 4)
      Materials include lists of missing work, collection tour information, requests for art use and return receipts.
    - C.A.A.M. exhibit, 1999-2004 (Box 272, Folder 5)
      Materials include contact lists, loan contracts and correspondence.
    - Art collection catalog, circa 2000 (Box 272, Folder 6)
      Golden State Mutual's Distinguished Art Collection Catalog includes color photo copies of the art work, artist names, creation dates and medium.
    - Art Tour Info, 2001-2002, 2004 (Box 272, Folder 7)
      Materials include C.A.A.M./GSM contact list, GSM 2001 Annual Report, artist biographies, A Brief History of... GSM, tour guide script and legend, collection inventory and a print out of an oral history interview with Charles Alston.
    - Appraisal report, 2002 December 5 (Box 272, Folder 8)
      This appraisal report was prepared for Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company by Eric Hanks of M. Hanks Gallery. The report includes photos of John T. Riddle's art work, correspondence between Hanks and GSM Director of Advertising and Public Relations and copies of appraisal reports.
    - Art collection inventories, 2002 (Box 273, Folder 1)
      Inventories include artist, title, medium, dimension, location and conservation priority.
    - Appraisal reports, 2002-2003 (Box 273, Folder 2)
      Materials include appraisal reports by Eric Hanks for works by the following artists: Charles Alston, Richmond Barthe, John Biggers, Elizabeth Catlett, Jacob Lawrence, Hughie Lee-Smith, William Pajaud, John T. Riddle, Henry Tanner, Charles White and Hale Woodruff.
    - Art work correspondence, 2002-2004 (Box 273, Folder 3)
      Materials include correspondence with the C.A.A.M., loan forms for 11 works by John T. Riddle and appraisal reports for these pieces.
    - LAMAG loans, 2004-2005 (Box 273, Folder 4)
      Materials include copies of loan agreements for the Los Angeles Municipal Art Gallery (LAMAG) "African American Artists in Los Angeles, A Survey Exhibition: Pathways," correspondence and appraisal report.
    - Swann Auction Galleries, 2007 (Box 273, Folder 5)
      Materials include correspondence between Larkin Teasley and Swann Galleries Director of African-American Fine Art, Nigel Freeman, a list of 100 items from GSM's art collection with auction estimates and a copy of the consignment agreement.
    - Art collection listings, undated (Box 273, Folder 6)
      Three art collection listings include artist name, title of work, medium, value, owner and location.
    - White on Black Art kit, undated (Box 273, Folder 7)
      White on Black Art community leader kit includes a letter from Ivan J. Houston concerning the audiovisual presentation narrated by Charles White which takes viewers on a tour of the GSM Afro-American Art Collection, an art collection booklet and list of schools in Southeast Los Angeles.
    - Artist profiles clipping, undated (Box 273, Folder 8)
      Clipping includes profiles for the following artists: Richmond Barthe, Richard Hunt, Charles White and John Biggers.
    - Exhibit labels, undated (Box 273, Folder 9)
      Materials include 18 exhibit labels attached to cardstock. The labels include the following information: Title, artist, medium, loaned by GSM and number.
    - The GSM Afro-American Art Collection, undated (Box 273, Folder 10)
      Materials include William Pajaud's transcript of a presentation about the creation and growth of GSM's Afro-American Art Collection.
    - Publications, 1937, 1947, 1968, 1974, 1976, 1979, 1981, 1984-1987, 1993-2000, 2004-2005, 2009 (Box 273, Box 274, Box 275)
      Publications in the GSM Afro-American Art Collection files are arranged chronologically and brief listed by title.
      Box 273: Joseph Nicolosi Sculpture catalogs, The Humble Way catalog, The International Review of African American Art, G. Ray Hawkins Gallery brochure, Black Art: an international quarterly, The Museum of African American Art brochure, Elizabeth Catlett exhibition program, GSM Afro-American Art Collection booklet, Varying Directions of Contemporary Black Artists exhibition program, The Towers of Simon Rodia in Watts map and brochure, The Museum of African American Art, Los Angeles exhibition catalog for "Los Angeles Collects" and The William Grant Still Community Arts Center catalog. (1937, 1947, 1968, 1974, 1976, 1979, 1981, 1984-1987)
      Box 274: African American Art: 20th Century Masterworks and two copies of The Art Riddle Contest, a children's book which features Hale Woodruff's GSM mural panel. (1993-2000)
      Box 275: The Art of John Biggers: View from the Upper Room exhibition book, Seeing Jazz: Artists and Writers on Jazz book, Royal-Athena Art Galleries catalogs, African American Artists in Los Angeles: A Survey exhibition catalog and two sets of GSM's Negro Art Collection cards. (1995, 1997, 2004-2005, 2009)
    - Photographs and proof sheets, 1965, 1968, 1975, 1978, 1980, 1993 (Box 276, Box 277)